Guide to the James Buchanan Duke Papers, 1777-1990 and undated
James Buchanan Duke papers 1777-1990 and undated
- Estate Series, 1777-1934, and undated (bulk 1926-1928)
  - Financial Papers Subseries, 1925-1934
    - Check stubs:
      - The Farmers' Loan and Trust Company, 1925, Oct. 11-1928, Sept. 13
      - Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1925, Oct. 11-1934, June 18 (2 folders)
    - Cancelled checks:
      - Bankers Trust Co., 1925-1928
      - Farmers' Loan and Trust, 1925-1928, Sept. 13
      - Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1925-1928, (3 folders)
    - Cancelled checks: Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1929-1934, (2 folders) (Box 53)
    - Legal and other fees paid, 1928
    - Federal Income Tax, 1925-1934, (10 folders)
    - Federal Estate Tax, 1931
    - State and local taxes, 1925-1934
  - Printed Materials Subseries, 1925-1926, undated
    Includes publications used by the executors to substantiate their legal case.
    - Handbook of County Records (N.C.), 1924
    - Handwriting Expert Testimony, undated
    - Confederate Homes and Pensions (public law), undated
    - Eleventh Biennial Report of the N.C. Historical Commission, 1924-1926
- Miscellaneous Series, 1890-1990, undated
  Includes printed material; clippings; a scrapbook of business (especially hydroelectric power), philanthropic and family subjects; a list of charitable contributions; a birth certificate; a history of the Inman family; a genealogical chart; biographical information; memorials; resolutions; blueprints of land plats and buildings; and architectural drawings. There are three subseries: General, Clippings, and Printed Materials. See also oversize materials. Arranged by subseries, then alphabetically by subject, title, or author's name (when known).
  - General Subseries, 1890-1970s, undated
    - Biography: Nanaline H. Duke, ca. 1970s; family history, Inman family, undated (Box 53)
    - Birth certificate, Doris Duke, 1912
    - Charitable contributions, 1890-1925
    - Passports: James B., Nanaline, and Doris Duke, 1923
    - Proof for commemorative plate: Signing The Duke Endowment, undated
    - Scrapbook: Business, philanthropic, family, undated (Box 54)
    - Tailoring dimensions, James B. Duke, ca. 1909-1923, undated
  - Clippings Subseries, 1898-1990, undated
    - Doris Duke, 1937, 1964-1990
    - Item VI of J.B. Duke's will, 1927-1928
    - House and estates: New York and North Carolina, 1913-1978
    - House and estate: Somerville, New Jersey, 1903-1987
    - Miscellaneous, 1898-1986, undated
  - Printed Materials Subseries, 1919-1982, undated
    - Subjects:
      - Advertisements [?], Spanish newspapers, 1919
      - Biographical statements about James B. Duke, 1952-1982, undated
      - Biography of Eugene Healan Thomason, with biographical note on J.B. Duke, undated
      - Memorials:
        - The Duke Endowment, Death of James B. Duke, 1925
        - Furman University,; James B. Duke, 1926
      - Programs: Duke University, Annual memorial service, 1939
        - Johnson C. Smith, 89th Anniversary, 1956
        - Memorial service for James B. Duke, 1925
      - Resolutions: Death of Benjamin N. Duke
        - by The Duke Endowment, 1919
        - by Duke Power Co., 1929
      - Resolution: Death of James B. Duke, by Piedmont and Northern Railway Co., 1926
    - Titles:
      - The American Tobacco Story, 1962
      - In A Carolina Forest, [Duke University] Time, 1931, Apr. 27
      - In Memoriam, James B. Duke, Alumni Register of Duke University, 1925, Nov.
      - Saguenay River Developments, 1921, undated
      - The New Empire of the Saguenay, 1926
      - Saguenay River Trip, 1923
    - Authors: (Box 55)
      - Allen, George G., Address Commemorating the Ninth Anniversary of The Duke Endowment, 1933
      - Cash, W.J., Buck Duke's University, in The American Mercury, 1933, Sept.
      - Durden, Robert F., Troubled Legacy: James B. Duke's Bequest to His Cousins (reprint), 1973
      - Fox, John W., Outline of Development of Duke Power Company, 1952
      - Hunt, Roy A, The Aluminum Pioneers, 1951
      - Rickey, James W., Hydro Power for the Production of Aluminum, 1936
      - Teague, Katherine, A Twentieth Century King Midas ? James B. Duke, undated
      - Towe, Kenneth C., Remarks Before the N.Y. Society of Security Analysts, 1955; William Brown Bell, [American Cyanamid Co.], 1953
      - Watson, E.A. and L. McW., Lynchburg Tobacco Imprints, in The Iron Worker, 1950-1951
- Pictures Series, 1870s-1960s, undated (bulk 1910s)
  Subjects include family, friends, and colleagues of James Buchanan Duke and buildings, homes, and estates. The motion picture film was copied from a silent movie on cellulose nitrate film. An album is first, followed by loose pictures, and then motion pictures. Negatives from the album have been separated from prints to allow for improved housing and preservation, and are not available for general reference use. Loose pictures are arranged alphabetically by name of person or by subject.
  - Album: Mildred K. Baldwin: (Box 56)
    - Duke family and inter-related family members; properties, 1910-1925, 1950 (2 folders)
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P., 1910s
    - Duke, James B., 1925
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N. with others, 1925
    - Duke Farms, Somerville, N.J., 1920s
    - Fairview, home of Washington Duke, ca. 1910-1925
  - People:
    - Daily, Betty Roney (Mrs. John C.), undated
    - Duke, Benjamin N., undated
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P., undated
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P. with family, 1890s-1910s
    - Duke, Doris christening a ship (SS James B. Duke?), 1944
    - Duke, James B.:
      - 1870s, ca. 1920s, undated, (3 folders)
      - Painting by John DaCosta, undated
      - Engraving, ca. 1905
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N., undated
    - Duke, James B., Benjamin N. and Washington; Erwin, NC, 1902-1903
    - Duke, James B. with B. N. Duke and G. W. Watts, undated
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N. with others, undated
    - Duke, James B. and Doris, 1919
    - Duke, James Buchanan, and Dula, Caleb C., undated
    - Duke, James B. with family and friends [at Myers Park?], undated
    - Duke, James B., fishing trip, undated
    - Duke, James B., funeral, 1925 (2 folders)
    - Duke, Nanaline H., 1915
    - Duke, Sarah P., undated
    - Duke, Washington, undated
    - Few, William P.;; Few, Mary R. with Frank Rounds, 1960s
    - Inman, Walker P., undated
    - Perkins, William R., 1933; Pickens, Marshall I., undated
    - Roney, Amos Kendall, undated; Roney, Artelia, undated
    - Sands, Alexander H., undated
    - Spence, Hersey Everett and Bessy W. with Frank Rounds, 1960s
  - Pictures: Mildred K. Baldwin Album (Box 56-A)
    - Duke family and inter-related family members, ca. 1910-1925
    - Duke family and inter-related family members, 1910-1925; 1950
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P., 1910s
    - Duke, James B., 1925
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N. with others, 1925
    - Duke Farms, Somerville, NJ, 1920s
    - "Fairview," home of Washington Duke, ca. 1910-1925
  - Negatives: Mildred K. Baldwin Album (Box 56-B)
    - Duke family and inter-related family members, ca. 1910-1925
    - Duke family and inter-related family members, 1910-1925; 1950
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P., 1910s
    - Duke, James B., 1925
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N. with others, 1925
    - Duke Farms, Somerville, NJ, 1920s
    - "Fairview," home of Washington Duke, ca. 1910-1925
    - Copy negative of portrait of J.B. and B.N. Duke
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin N.
    - Duke, James B., Benjamin N., and Washington, Erwin, NC, 1902-1903
    - Duke, James Buchanan and Dula, Caleb C.
    - Duke, Benjamin N.
    - Duke, James B. and Benjamin with others
    - Duke, Benjamin N. and Sarah P.
  - Subjects: (Box 57)
    - Duke Homestead and buildings, undated
    - Somerville, N.J., Estate:
      - Postcards, 1909, undated
      - Identified areas, undated, (3 folders)
      - Architectural drawing by Horace Trumbauer, ca. 1911
    - Southern Power Co., laying cornerstone, Catawba River, S.C., 1905
    - Quebec Development Company, Saguenay River, Quebec Canada:, (3 folders)
      - 5 photographic postcards of scenes of Alma, Isle Malique and Mixer house fire, 1924, undated
      - 23 photographic postcards of scenes from the construction of Isle Malign Station, undated
      - 3 photos of Isle Malign on Saguenay River, undated
      - 2 photos of staff of Quebec Development Company - identified individuals: D.F. Noyes, S.W. Myatt, Frank Harrison, undated
      - 10 photographs of construction of Isle Malign Station in Paper Manufactures' Souvenir, 1924
      - 1 photographic map of Saguenay River in Programme of Summer Meeting for Saguenay Branch of the Engineering Institute of Canada, 1924, June 6.
  - Motion pictures: (Box 58)
    - J.B. Duke and Caleb C. Dula at Dula residence, Yonkers, N.Y. ( copy film)
      - negative, undated
    - J.B. Duke and Caleb C. Dula at Dula residence, Yonkers, N.Y. ( copy film)
      - print, undated
- Oversize Materials
  - Business Papers Series
    - Southern Power Company:
      - Maps of transmission system, 1922, undated (Box 59)
    - Orlando Water Power Corporation:
      - Financial statements: Worksheets, 1916-1922; Patents: Italian, 1913-1920; Plan (blueprint) showing transmission line, undated (Box 59)
    - Duke Farms Company:
      - Accounts, 1922-1922; financial statements, 1916-1925; income taxes, 1918-1919 (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Southern Investment Company of Delaware,; Southern Investment Company of New Jersey:
      - Financial statements: worksheets, 1912-1922 (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Financial Papers Series
    - Miscellaneous financial statements of James B. Duke, 1913-1925, undated (Box 59)
  - Estate Series:
    - Legal Papers Subseries
      - Discovery: Duke family history, undated (Box 59)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Charts showing kinship to John Roney and Taylor Duke, undated; proof for cast of commemorative plate, undated; Clippings, 1907 (Box 59)
    - Diploma from Eastman National Business College 1875, September 8 (Opaperfolder 6)
    - Property and houses (blueprints):
      - Melon house (proposed), Duke Farms Co., Somerville, N.J., 1917, Aug.; Conservatory of Music, Durham, N.C., land plat, 1913; Main Street Methodist Episcopal Church, Durham, N.C., land plats, 1913; First Methodist Episcopal Church, Somerville, N.J., floor plans, 1923 (Box 59)
    - Property and houses:
      - Land plats for Myers Park, Charlotte, N.C., 1919; Blueprints for laundry in residence, Myers Park, 1922 (Opaperfolder 3)
      - Architectural plans by Horace Trumbauer for 78th St., New York, N.Y., residence, 1909 (Opaperfolder 4)
  - Pictures Series
    - Angier B. Duke, ca. 1923 (Box 59)
    - James B. Duke, undated (Box 59)
    - Washington Duke, undated (Box 59)
    - Buildings and property:
      - Duke Chapel Methodist Episcopal Church, South, (; Horace Trumbauer drawings) Bragtown, N.C., undated; Duke Homestead, undated; Duke's first factory (barn), undated; Duke's mixture factory, undated (Box 59)
    - Benjamin N. Duke, undated (Box 59)
    - Staff and owners of British-American Tobacco Co. on the SS James B. Duke, undated (Opaperfolder 5)